Among China's eight main cuisines
it's Sichuan fare that's the most popular
(Sichuan Cuisine)
widely served
and evocative of local culture
It's because the bulk of
Sichuan's toothsome dishes
originate in local households
(Folk Gastronomy)
It's home cooking
(Home Cooking)
It's all around the country
(All around the Country)
Among them all, Sichuan-style dishes
(Most Irresistible)
are the most popular
(Most Delectable)
Exotic flavors
conjured from
ceaseless spicy experimentation
constitute the very soul of Sichuan Cuisine
and its universal appeal
No fish is added to fish-flavored shredded pork
But the dish
(No Fish)
has a fishy flavor
I think it contains fish
(Fish)
The flavor is not from fish
(Not from fish)
It's a matter of philosophy
(A Matter of Philosophy)
Tasting it is a moment of epicurean wonder
Wow, delicious
(Delicious)
This series presents Sichuan Cuisines'
six most representative and influential dishes
Seemingly ordinary
each one has
an intriguing
back story
(Sichuan Cuisine)
(Mapo Tofu)
(Bagong Mountain)
This is Bagong Mountain
in Anhui provinces, Shouxian County
The lush forests
and fresh, humid air here
is the perfect setting for human self-cultivation
Over 2,100 years ago
a group of people gathered here
to pursue immortality
This group of sculptures depicts
eight gentlemen led by Liu An, Prince of Huainan
of the Han Dynasty
In the course of
concocting an elixir with spring water
soybeans, and calcium sulfate
inadvertently they invented tofu
Ming Dynasty pioneer of medical science Li Shizhen
recorded that tofu's existence
is attributable to Liu An
Liu An failed to achieve immortality
and was buried in Bagong Mountain after death
But the tofu he invented became a facet of China's
if not global culinary history
Tofu is an amazingly versatile
culinary ingredient
Celebrated Qing Dynasty writer and gourmet Yuan Mei
(Yuan Mei (1716-1798))
wrote in his recipes from
the Garden of Contentment
(The tofu tastes even better than bird's nest soup)
This seemingly arbitrary statement
refers to tofu's ability as an ingredient
in itself, tasteless
to be adapted to a wide spectrum of flavors, a talent
none other can match
The capacity
to tone down strong flavored ingredients
and enriched bland ones
is a distinctive feature
of Chinese cuisine
Tofu's capacity to absorb
a wide range of flavors
while retaining
its original texture
makes it perfect for
exotically seasoned Sichuan Cuisine
Delicious tofu dishes abound throughout China
but till today
none enjoy the fame and favor
of Mapo Tofu
which originated 150 years ago
in Chengdu
(Chengdu, Sichuan Province)
During Qing Emperor Tongzhi's reign
around 1862
by the Wanfu Bridge in Chengdu North Gate
the Chen Xinsheng restaurant
(Depiction of Culinary Customs in Old Chengdu)
was opened
by Chen Chunfu and his wife
The Wanfu Bridge
was an important transportation passage for grain and oil
porters generally stopped there to rest and dine
As they transported the oil from the North Gate
there were often dregs of rapeseed oil
(Chen Shi
Cooking Master)
left in the buckets
that had been carried over the bridge
which later they would give to the restaurant proprietress
to cook tofu on their way back
After mincing the fresh beef
she would fry it on a moderate heat
and then add the tofu and spicy sauce
(Depiction of Culinary Customs in Old Chengdu)
Mrs. Chen's
spicy and aromatic tofu
was the perfect accompaniment to rice
The devastatingly delicious combination
rapidly became the favorite of hungry porters
and diners generally
Known as
Mapo Chen
due to her facial pock marks
her famous tofu dish
was known as Mapo Tofu
Since its birth
it has been widely welcomed among the public
and has been included in the 1909 Chengdu Review
among Chengdu's most famous dishes
(Mapo Chen's Tofu)
Old Chengdu Tales
published in the Republic of China period says
in the part of snacks that
Mapo Chen at the North Gate
excelled at cooking tofu
and it cost only 8 cents per bowl
including the seasonings
Few remember the name of the restaurant
but everyone knew Mapo Chen
Although far from the downtown area
her place never lacked diners
Mapo Chen would be astounded to know that
her simple and delicious tofu dish
has retained its popularity
both throughout China and overseas, too
acting as an ambassador of Chinese cuisine
How could this home-style cooking
captivate so many?
Does the answer lie in its cooking process?
Inherited from history
both Chen's Mapo Tofu shop and its recipe
are now time-honored
Chinese brands
Therefore, the standard Mapo Tofu dish
must fulfill the requirements of being
mouth-numbingly spicy, fresh, appetizing, crisp, tender, and hot
It may appear simple
but to the uninitiated, cooking this dish is a challenge
Mastering certain subtleties
can take as long as three to five years
Choosing the tofu is the first step
There are in China two broad categories
of southern and northern tofu
which differ in both flavor and texture
The coagulant of southern or soft tofu
is calcium sulfate
while bittern is used for northern or firm tofu
Normally
Mapo Tofu
uses the northern firm tofu
The northern tofu made with bittern
has small holes
whereby the entire slab of tofu
(Zhang Huiqiang, Curator
Sichuan Cuisine Museum)
absorbs flavor during the cooking process
The evolution of Sichuan Cuisine
has inevitably created expressions
in the Sichuan dialect
for special cooking skills
"Du" is one of them
This character isn't in the dictionary
but to me, it has two meanings
Firstly "du" means controlling the heat
If you're cooking on a medium fire
you must constantly check it
to avoid impairing the flavor
The second is onomatopoeic
referring to the sound the dish makes while being cooked
Thickening by adding cornstarch
at the appropriate time is a crucial step
But what's rarely known is that
they must be expertly carried out three times
with attention paid to the method
Constarch is added to reduce water
that seeps from the tofu during the cooking process
(Zhang Huiqiang, Curator
Sichuan Cuisine Museum)
As the heating continues
tofu seeps water for the second time
constarch is added to reduce water again
Such thickening takes place
at three progressive stages of cooking
after which no water remains in the tofu
In this way
a thin layer of cornstarch
is formed over each tofu cube
(Zhang Zhengxiong
Cooking Master)
Coating the tofu cubes with cornstarch
gives them a soft
and flawless look
and also keeps them tender
and hot
The finishing touch
of tossing and serving the tofu
gives it a tantalizing glow
that diners find irresistible
Such subtle touches
distinguish professionals from amateurs
Rigorous training
helps master chefs
establish their reputations
and gain international fame
But some choose to work over the same stove
for a lifetime
We now know that
Mapo Chen invented Mapo Tofu
over a century ago
But it was the innovations of someone else
a man named Xue Xiangshun that created the dish we know today
(Xue Xiangshun)
(A 3,000 dish repertoire beats eternal fame)
said Li Shuren
former president of Sichuan Gourmet Association
The old man, now in his seventies
has tasted all delicacies in his life
But for him, no dish could come close to
Xue Xiangshun's Mapo Tofu
During the 1940s
Li studied at a school adjacent to the Wanfu Bridge
He and his classmates
dined daily at Mapo Chen's restaurant for three years
The original proprietress having passed away
Chef Xue Xiangshun was her apprentice
(During my 3 years at high school)
(My classmates and I would)
(gather at the stove to watch Master Xue Xiangshun apply his skills)
(Clad in a blue gown)
(and straw sandals all year round)
(he was slim and fit-looking)
(Not giving the conversation, he was totally absorbed in his cooking)
(In the ensuing decades)
(Mapo Chen's restaurant weathered various fluctuations)
(But no matter what changes occurred)
(Master Xue carried on cooking over his stove)
(until his death in the 1970s)
(constantly improving this dish)
(and freely passing on the skills)
(Xue Xiangshun)
(to succeeding generations)
(Good diners present happiness, while good cooks present benevolence)
(A true chef is a virtuous, kind-hearted and taciturn man)
(pursuing his culinary creations at the kitchen)
(Master Xue Xiangshun was exactly such a person)
(Che Fu
Gourmet)
Celebrated gourmet Che Fu
wrote down the entire cooking process of
Xue Xiangshun's Mapo Tofu in his book
Sichuan Cuisine Miscellany
Master Xue did not
add broad bean paste, blanch
or thicken the tofu
(Main Ingredients of Xue Xiangshun's Mapo Tofu)
but his Mapo Tofu was nevertheless
fresh, tender, and savory
His method was to add oil to a pot
directly followed by the minced beef
When the beef was dry and crisp
he added fermented soybeans and chili powder
and then the tofu
into the hot wok
with oil and minced meat
After lightly stirring the dish
he added a little sauce
Once done
he checked to see
if it was ready to serve
or required some more stirs
Diners could then take delight in
the appetizing vision of his famous Mapo Tofu dish
During the 1950s
Xue Xiangshun started
using Pixian fermented broad bean paste for his dish
The innovations of generations of chefs
after his death in 1973
culminated in the contemporary recipe we know today
(Main Ingredients of Contemporary Mapo Tofu)
Nevertheless
each chef incorporates in it his or her
distinct culinary characteristic
(Xiba Town, Leshan, Sichuan Province)
The ancient peaceful town of Xiba
is said to serve the world's finest tofu
In the famous town of Sichuan Cuisine, Leshan
Xiba's tofu ranked the first
until it disbanded, the Sanba
one of Xiba's top restaurants
was the town's Supply and Marketing Cooperative Canteen
The Liu family then took it over
Its third generation manages the Sanba Restaurant today
Women have managed the restaurant
Zhou Yuqiong
whether as owner, chef, or waiting staff
It's a tradition
passed on till now
Rather than making Mapo Tofu with firm tofu
as most restaurants do
the Sanba Restaurant adds tender tofu to
its specially prepared crisp minced beef
The combination brings out the best in both
making it the perfect accompaniment to rice
The crisp minced beef
we have devised
distinguishes it from Mapo Tofu dishes elsewhere
as do the spring onions and Sichuan pepper incorporated in it
Eaten with rice
the taste is out of the word
(Li Yaohua
Cooking Master)
Mapo Tofu is delicious
beyond compare
The cooking process makes it
both hot and fresh
the perfect complement to rice
Minced meat
either pork or beef
is a fundamental ingredient
But
famous writer and gourmet
Wang Zengqi advised in his essay Tofu
(Firstly, ample oil is needed. Secondly, use minced beef)
(I made Mapo Tofu many times)
(but it just didn't taste right)
(Only later did I realize it was because I had used minced pork)
(Minced pork is no substitute for minced beef)
(You need to taste it)
(the moment the dish is presented)
(even if you are chatting or drinking)
(Mapo Tofu is essentially)
(mouth-numbingly spicy and hot)
(Yuan Tingdong
Chengdu Folklore Scholar)
There are many descriptions
of Mapo Chen's tofu
but the one closest to my own is
that by Mr. Li Jieren
mouth-numbing, spicy, crisp, tender, hot, fresh, and complete
in seven words
Calling tofu "crisp" seems odd
but it relates to the minced beef
Sichuan Cuisine encompasses a way of cooking
called "nan"
It means slowly heating minced beef
over a mild heat
instead of stir-frying
or sauteing
until all the water has gone
and it turns crisp
(Japan)
Mapo Tofu
is the most popular Chinese dish
in Japan
Its fame is inextricable from a certain man from Sichuan
(Material)
On November 10th, 1952
a ship heading for Yokohama
set sail from Hong Kong
One of the passengers
brought with him
a kitchen knife, a fry pan, a chopping board
and even tableware
The man
was Chen Kenmin
from Fushun, Sichuan
(Chen Kenmin)
In 1958
Chen Kenmin opened a restaurant in Tokyo
Mapo Tofu has since
been the most popular dish among its diners
Chen Kenmin's constant recommendation of the dish
on TV shows helped Mapo Tofu
become the favorite Chinese dish
of the Japanese people
In 1987
the Japanese government
awarded Chen Kenmin
the title "Modern Master"
a prize intended to encourage and honor
(Chen Kenmin)
the talent and potential of those with outstanding skills
in all industries
In 2008
Chen Kenichi
Chen Kenmin's son
also won this award
(Chen Kenichi)
Nowadays
every Sichuan Cuisine restaurant in Japan
serves Mapo Tofu
The chefs may not necessarily be from Sichuan
But they are skilled at cooking
the authentic Mapo Tofu dish
Popular throughout the country and globally too
Mapo Tofu displays a variability
reminiscent of Sichuan opera's face-changing technique
The constant creativity of chefs
who regularly add new dishes featuring Mapo Tofu
to the restaurant menus
never fails to amaze
Sichuan Cuisine aficionados
(Chongqing)
Mapo Tofu and pizza
served at an office building
in central Chongqing
may seem an incongruous combination
But local diners relish this blending of Chinese and western ingredients
owner of this pizza restaurant
(He Xiaojiang)
was once a chef of a western-style restaurant
in a five-star hotel
also adept at Sichuan Cuisine
He has successfully
blended Chinese and western ingredients
Fusing the fresh fragrance of cheese
with the mouth-numbing spiciness of Mapo Tofu
is the key to combining Mapo Tofu and pizza
without losing their original features
While making the pizza
he substitutes a mouth-numbingly spicy sauce
for the traditional ingredients of
Sichuan pepper and broad bean paste
and uses firm tofu
As the pizza bakes
the tofu absorbs the taste
of both the cheese and sauce
lining every bite of cheese with crisp and soft and tender tofu
Wu Yunwei is less than 40 years old
but nevertheless, a cooking master in China
He's about to make Mapo Tofu oysters
Soft, tender
and fresh tasting oysters
are normally either char-grilled or steamed
When a year ago
Wu Yunwei paid a visit to Japan
to exchange cooking skills
he was impressed at the Japanese people's passion for Mapo Tofu
During a chat with friends an idea suddenly came to him
As Japan abounds in seafood
(Wu Yunwei
Cooking Master)
I wondered about serving oysters with Mapo Tofu
That night
an idea jumped into our mind
We combine traditional Mapo Tofu with seafood
The seafood's freshness accentuates deliciously
the mouth-numbing spiciness of Mapo Tofu
Not only is Mapo Tofu oyster
mouth-numbingly spicy
and redolent of classic street food
but also oyster fresh
Liu An and his friends' inadvertent invention of tofu
from beans sparked infinite gastronomic possibilities
In the Book of Tofu
the global bestseller also known as the Tofu Bible
the author remarks how to him
the Tai Chi diagram resembles a stone mill
whose grinding initiates the beans'
flow of nutrition
and also transformation
After immersion in water
the beans are ground into soybean milk
and start their journey of change
from plain beans to the globally famed Mapo Tofu
Their story evokes
the daily lives of ordinary people
who emit a similar glow
in the course of their creativity and transformation